Guide to the Max Worthington Papers 1926-1990
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Max Worthington Papers
1926-1990
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Worthington, Max, 1909-2003
2433
1.2 linear feet
The Max Worthington Papers consist of a scrapbook chronicling his career, personal and professional correspondence, and photographs. Subjects present in the collection include the Montana State "Golden Bobcats;" the Sigma Alpha Epsilon fraternity; college football, basketball and track teams; the Helms Athletic Foundation Hall of Fame; the Montana State University Hall of Fame; Montana high school athletics; Worthington Arena; Max Worthington's retirement party; "Golden Bobcat" reunions; and the Montana Special Olympics.
This collection is open for research.
The Max Worthington Papers were donated to both the MSU Archives and Special Collections by Max Worthington in several deposits between 1979 and 2001. These separate donated accessions (#2433, #78012, #90069, #92009, #92041, #94009 and #94057) have been integrated into one collection.
Series 1: Scrapbooks and scrapbook materials, 1926-1990
Series 2: Correspondence, 1932-1989
Series 3: Photographs, 1926-1980s
Max Worthington was born Oct 7, 1909 in Billings, Montana. He was a star athlete at Billings High School in both football and basketball. He started his college career at Montana State College (now Montana State University, Bozeman) in the fall of 1927. He continued his football and basketball careers from his freshman year, most notably as a member of the Montana State "Golden Bobcats" basketball team. In 1932, he graduated with a bachelor's degree in Physical Education. He took a job as a coach and teacher in Shelby, Montana from 1932 - 1938. In 1933, he married Dorothy Douglas of Wisdom, Montana, and they had one son, Douglas. In 1938, he moved to Helena High School, where in 1942 he became Director of Athletics. In 1943, he joined the U.S. Navy and served in the Pacific Theater. After the war, he joined the Montana State College faculty in 1946 as Assistant Professor of Physical Education and Assistant Football Coach and Basketball Coach. In 1948, he became the Associate Director of Public Service, and in 1950, the Secretary of the Alumni Association. In 1964, he was appointed Dean of Student Affairs and Service, a post he held until his retirement in 1973. As Dean of Students Emeritus, Max lived in Bozeman and continued to support the athletic events of the Bobcats and other university programs until his death in 2003.
Max Worthington's personal papers have been arranged into three series. Series 1 includes: a scrapbook and many scrapbook materials from his long career which include newspaper clippings, programs, postcards, social ephemera, brochures, World War II naval papers, collected materials of personal interest (including a Richard Nixon autograph), one oral interview, testimonials and certificates. Series 2 consists of personal and professional correspondence. (Researchers are reminded that official records generated by Max Worthington in his capacity as an MSU faculty member and administrator are held within the pertinent record groups within the University Archives.) Series 3 consists of photographs. Subjects present in the collection include the Montana State "Golden Bobcats;" the Sigma Alpha Epsilon fraternity; college football, basketball and track teams; the Helms Athletic Foundation Hall of Fame; the Montana State University Hall of Fame; Montana high school athletics; Worthington Arena; Max Worthington's retirement party; "Golden Bobcat" reunions; and the Montana Special Olympics. Individuals prominently featured are Ott Romney, J. Ashworth "Cat" Thompson, Frank Ward, Orland Ward, Valery Glynn, John "Brick" Breeden, Schubert Dyche, Marjorie Paisley, Roland R. Renne, Tony Storti, Jan Stenerud, Lones Wigger and Bill Duncan.
Breeden, John W., 1904-1977; Duncan, Bill, 1897-1967; Dyche, Schubert, 1893-1982; Glynn, Val G., 1903-1992; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Paisley, Marjorie, 1909-2001; Renne, Roland Roger, 1905-1989; Romney, G. Ott-(George Ottinger), 1892-1973; Stenerud, Jan, 1942-; Storti, Tony; Thompson, J. Ashworth-(John Ashworth), 1906-1990; Ward, Frank; Ward, Orland; Wigger, Lones
Golden Bobcats (Basketball team); Montana State University--Bozeman--Alumni and alumnae; Montana State University--Bozeman-Basketball; Montana State University--Bozeman--Faculty; Montana State University--Bozeman-Football; Montana State University--Bozeman-Sports; Montana State University--Bozeman-Track and field; Sigma Alpha Epsilon; United States-Navy-History-World War, 1939-1945; Worthington Arena (Bozeman, Mont.)
Basketball teams-Montana-Bozeman; College sports-Montana-Bozeman; Football teams-Montana-Bozeman; Halls of fame-Montana-Bozeman; School sports-Montana; Special Olympics; Track and field-Montana-Bozeman; Veterans-Montana-Bozeman; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations, American; World War, 1939-1945-Veterans-Montana-Bozeman; Basketball players-Montana-Bozeman; Coaches (Athletics)-Montana-Bozeman; Deans (Education)--Montana--Bozeman
Colleges and Universities; Military; Sports and Recreation; Montana; Bozeman; Montana; Oral Histories; Photographs; Scrapbooks
Oral histories; Photographs; Interviews; Albums (Books); Scrapbooks
- Scrapbooks and scrapbook materials, 1926-1990; Series 1
  Series one contains materials and papers accumulated by Max Worthington from his high school years to the late 1980s. A substantial scrapbook of college days includes his sports career and his membership in the Sigma Alpha Epsilon. Photographs of classmates and fraternity brothers along with newspaper clippings, correspondence, social ephemera and brochures are present. There are numerous newspaper clipping files about the "Golden Bobcats," WWII, athletics and special events at Montana State University, legislation of the 1980s affecting the University system, the career of sports writer Bill Duncan and other diverse subjects. A comprehensive group of military records trace his service in the Naval Reserve on active duty from 1943-1946 in the Pacific Theater during WWII. His recognition as a significant athletic of the 1920-30s is represented by files of programs, tributes, souvenirs and certificates for the Montana State College Hall of Fame, Worthington Arena, and alumni reunions. Files of materials for the 1989 Montana Special Olympics, artwork of a grateful student, a group of Dorothy Worthington's employment records, legislative information of the 1980s, an audio tape interview for the 75th anniversary of the university, retirement party records, a Richard Nixon autograph and a selection of diverse memorabilia completes the series. Groups of materials are arranged in approximate chronological order.
  - Scrapbook, 1926-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1929-1930 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clippings: WWII (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings: athletics, Montana State University (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper clippings: Bill Duncan (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper clippings: 80s legislation (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper clippings, miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Military service: application, commission (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Military service: orders (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Military service: training (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Military service: U.S.A.T. Sea Barb (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Military service: U.S.A.T. Evangeline (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Military service: travel vouchers and equipment inventories (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Military service: medical (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Military service: life insurance (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Military service: postwar papers (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Military service: certificates, dog tag, identification cards (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Military service: memorabilia (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Audiotape of 75th anniversary of university, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Retirement party (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - MSU Hall of Fame programs and application forms (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Worthington Arena (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Alumni: team lists of football, basketball and track members (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Assorted dedication programs (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dorothy Worthington, employment papers, 1955-1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Richard Nixon autograph (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Certificates: Max and Dorothy Worthington, 1928-1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Legislation: admission standards, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Legislation: referendums, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Legislation: rural areas development, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Legislation: miscellaneous, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Special Olympics, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
  - Artwork from student: Mustapha Ghaddar (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Diverse memorabilia: poetry, stories, brochures and miscellaneous souvenirs (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1932-1989; Series 2
  Correspondence collected by Max Worthington has been arranged in chronological order with special files for retirement and Hall of Fame congratulatory letters and a file of letters between Max Worthington and sports writer Bill Duncan.
  - Correspondence, 1932-1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Bill Duncan, 1966-1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Retirement, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1985 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: MSU Hall of Fame, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Photographs, 1926-1980s; Series 3
  Collected photographs include posed and candid shots of Max Worthington; athletic events, teams and reunions; university celebrations; WWII snap shots of shipmates, shipboard activities and ports of call. Two booklets of photographs chronicle some of the life in Lae, Papua New Guinea and the Papuan natives while stationed on the U.S.A.T. Sea Barb at Milne Bay, New Guinea with additional pictures of Leyte, the Philippines, and Australia. The final group of photos are in a ring binder which chronicles Max Worthington's 1973 retirement party with friends and colleagues of the university community.
  - Photograph #1-4: Max Worthington, individual and with others (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Photograph #5-6: Montana Basketball Championships (on court), 1926-1927 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Photograph #7-8: MSU reunions: basketball and track teams (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Photograph #9-39: Hall of Fame Banquet and Homecoming, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Photograph #40-61: various reunions including banquet for Ott Romney (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Photograph #62-63: snapshots of Hall of Fame and Worthington Arena plaques (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Photograph #64-87: WWII pictures of shipmates, ships, gunnery practice and ship life (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Photograph #88-117: WWII pictures of ports of call, native peoples and recreation (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Photograph #118-137: Retirement party photos in a ring binder (Box 4, Folder 26)